<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-09T13:08:43+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">SIGTACS</title><subtitle>Special Interest Group on Theoretical Aspects of Computer Science was born out of an effort to bring together people interested in areas of Theoretical Computer Science. It is a platform for students and faculty members to come together and share their excitement in the area. The group aims at organizing problem solving sessions, seminars and guest lectures.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Poly-time blackbox identity testing for sum of log-variate, constant-width ROABPs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/Pranav-Bisht.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Poly-time blackbox identity testing for sum of log-variate, constant-width ROABPs " /><published>2020-05-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/Pranav-Bisht</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/Pranav-Bisht.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk is based on joint work with Prof. Nitin Saxena. We explore blackbox PIT (Polynomial Identity Testing) problem for the model of “Sum of ROABPs (Read-once oblivious Algebraic Branching Programs)”. Recent bootstrapping results motivate us to study log-variate ROABPs. We also restrict the width of ROABP to a constant but study the more general sum-of-ROABPs model. We give the first poly($s$)-time blackbox PIT for sum of constant-many, size-$s$, $O(\log s)$-variate constant-width ROABPs. The
previous best for this model was a quasi-polynomial time which is comparable to brute-force in the log-variate setting. Also, we handle unbounded-many such ROABPs if each ROABP computes a homogeneous polynomial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our new techniques comprise– (1) a ROABP computing a homogeneous polynomial can be made syntactically homogeneous in the same width; and (2) overcome the hurdle of unknown variable order in sum-of-ROABPs in the log-variate setting (over any field).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the talk, we will begin from scratch with definitions of PIT and various models including ROABPs. Then, we shall discuss the motivations behind this model and its non-triviality. Finally, we will give a brief overview of the PIT algorithms and why they work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the paper for more detials: &lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/042/&quot;&gt;TR20-042&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> Pranav Bisht</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lower bounds on the sum of 25th-powers of univariates lead to complete derandomization of PIT</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/Pranjal-Dutta.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Lower bounds on the sum of 25th-powers of univariates lead to complete derandomization of PIT " /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/Pranjal-Dutta</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/Pranjal-Dutta.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consider the univariate polynomial $f_d := (x + 1)^d$ when represented as a sum of constant-powers of univariate polynomials. We define a natural measure for the model, the support-union, and conjecture that it is $\Omega(d)$ for $f_d$ .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We show a stunning connection of the conjecture to the two main problems in algebraic complexity: Polynomial Identity Testing (PIT) and VP vs. VNP. Our conjecture on f_d implies blackbox-PIT in P. Assuming the Generalized Riemann Hypothesis (GRH), it also implies VP $\neq$ VNP. No such connection to PIT, from lower bounds on constant-powers representation of polynomials was known before. We establish that studying the expression of $(x + 1)^d$ , as the sum of 25th-powers of univariates, suffices to solve the two major open questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is based on joint work (submitted) with Prof.  Nitin Saxena (IIT Kanpur) and Prof. Thomas Thierauf (Aalen University); see the paper for details: &lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/039/&quot;&gt;TR20-039&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> Pranjal Dutta</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Characterising Hardness for QBF Resolution via Circuit Complexity.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/Meena-Mahajan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Characterising Hardness for QBF Resolution via Circuit Complexity." /><published>2020-02-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/Meena-Mahajan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/Meena-Mahajan.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk will start with an overview of the relatively young field of QBF proof complexity, explaining QBF proof systems (including QBF resolution) and an assessment of which lower bound techniques are available for QBF proof systems. In the main part of the talk, I will explain hardness characterisations for QBF proof systems in terms of circuit complexity, yielding very direct connections between circuit lower bounds and QBF proof system lower bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint work with Olaf Beyersdorff and Joshua Blinkhorn. ECCC Technical Report &lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/005/&quot;&gt;TR20-005&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the Speaker:
Meena Mahajan is a professor at Institute of Mathematical Sciences, Chennai. She completed her B.Tech and M.Tech from IIT Bombay and her Ph.D.
at IIT Madras under Prof. Kamala Kritivasan. She has been a faculty at IMSc since 1994. She has extensively contributed in the area of
Computational Complexity Theory especially Algebraic Complexity, Circuit  Complexity, Proof Complexity and its connections to Automata.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> Prof. Meena Mahajan</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Matroid intersection</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/Anay-Mehrotra.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Matroid intersection" /><published>2020-02-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/Anay-Mehrotra</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/Anay-Mehrotra.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matroids are abstract structures which generalize the notion of linear independence in vector spaces. This lead to surprising connections to graph theory, combinatorial optimization, and topology. In this talk, we would introduce the idea of matroids in simple words, look at the idea of matroid intersection, and a greedy algorithm for finding it.
Outline/reference: &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeforces.com/blog/entry/69287&quot;&gt;https://codeforces.com/blog/entry/69287&lt;/a&gt;
The talk will be accessible to someone with knowledge of linear algebra, matrices, and basic graph algorithms (e.g., DFS, BFS, Kruskal’s/Prim’s minimum spanning tree algorithms).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> Anay Mehrotra</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Barrington’s Theorem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Abhibhav-Garg.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Barrington's Theorem" /><published>2020-01-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-01-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Abhibhav-Garg</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Abhibhav-Garg.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barrington’s theorem is a result in classical complexity which
states that any boolean function in NC^1 can be computed by a branching
program of bounded width. We will discuss the proof of this surprising
theorem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhibhav Garg</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Counterexamples to Hedetniemi’s Conjecture</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Nikhil-Shagrithaya.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counterexamples to Hedetniemi's Conjecture" /><published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Nikhil-Shagrithaya</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Nikhil-Shagrithaya.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensor product GxH of two graphs G and H has the vertex set $V(G)\times V(H)$, and the pairs $(g,h)$ and $(g’,h’)$ are adjacent if and only if $g$ is adjacent to $g`$ in G and $h$ is adjacent to $h$ in H. A proper colouring $g \to C(g)$ for graph $G$ can be ‘lifted’ to give a proper colouring $(g,h) \to C(g)$ for $G \times H$, and similarly a lifting can be done for a proper colouring of H as well. This implies that the minimum between the chromatic numbers of $G$ and $H$ forms an upper bound on the chromatic number of $G \times H$ (i.e, $X(G \times H) \leq \min(X(G), X(H)$). In 1966, S. Hedetniemi conjectured that equality holds for all finite simple graphs. In 2019, Yaroslav Shitov refuted the conjecture by constructing a counterexample using the concept of exponential graphs, which have vertices corresponding to every possible c-colouring of an n-vertex graph, with two vertices being adjacent only if the corresponding colourings paint every adjacent vertex with different colours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we will discuss exponential graphs in detail, and then look at the construction of the counterexample.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nikhil Shagrithaya</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cryptanalysis of Round-Reduced KECCAK using Non-linear Structures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Mahesh-SR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cryptanalysis of Round-Reduced KECCAK using Non-linear Structures" /><published>2020-01-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-01-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/%20Mahesh-SR</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/Mahesh-SR.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptographic hash functions are widely used in modern cryptography such as in digital signatures, message integrity and authentication. The U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) announced the “NIST hash function competition” for the Secure Hash Algorithm-3 (SHA-3) in 2006. They received 64 proposals from around the world. Among these, KECCAK designed by Bertoni, Daemen, Peeters, and Van Assche became one of the candidates for SHA-3. It won the competition in October 2012 and was standardized as a “Secure Hash Algorithm 3” .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we will look at new preimage attacks on KECCAK-384 and KECCAK-512 for 2, 3 and 4 rounds. The attacks are based on non-linear structures (structures that contain quadratic terms). These structures were studied by Guo et al. and Li et al. to give preimage attacks on round reduced KECCAK. We carefully construct non-linear structures such that the quadratic terms are not spread across the whole state. This allows us to create more linear equations between the variables and hash values, leading to better preimage attacks. As a result, we get the best theoretical preimage attack on KECCAK-384 and KECCAK-512 for 2 and 3-rounds and also KECCAK-384 for 4-rounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mahesh S R</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Complexity of Hilberts Nullstellensatz</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Shubhojyoti-Nath.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Complexity of Hilberts Nullstellensatz" /><published>2019-11-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Shubhojyoti-Nath</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Shubhojyoti-Nath.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hilbert’s Nullstellensatz is an important theorem in Commutative Algebra and Algebraic Geometry. It connects the notion of ideals (in Commutative Algebra) to that of varieties (in Algebraic Geometry). In this project, we investigate the computational version of this problem (HN) which basically translates to finding how hard is it to decide whether or not 1 lies in the ideal generated by a set of polynomials, say {f1, f2, …, fm} in k[x1, x2, …, xn]. In particular, we look at the two most important results pertaining to the complexity of the above problem (for field k of zero-characteristic): HN is in PSPACE, and under Generalized Riemann Hypothesis, HN is in AM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shubhojyoti Nath</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PIT of Depth-4 Constant Top and Bottom Fan-in Circuits</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Devansh-Shringi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PIT of Depth-4 Constant Top and Bottom Fan-in Circuits" /><published>2019-11-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Devansh-Shringi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Devansh-Shringi.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we will explore the problem of Polynomial Identity Testing (PIT) which is of finding an algorithm that checks if a given polynomial is zero or not in polynomial time. The problem is central to the field of Algebraic complexity and has known connections to lower bounds, as well as other problems in complexity theory. It has a simple randomized black-box solution but a deterministic algorithm is not known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will take a look at the restricted class of circuits of depth-4 constant Top and Bottom Fan-in. Solving the problem for the depth-4 case will imply a solution for the general PIT using depth reduction in [AV08]. The case of constant top Fan in depth-3 has been solved for both white-box [KS07] and black-box [SS13] cases. Thus, this remains the next unsolved case in the field, for which even the white-box solution is not known. We will look at the conjectures in [Gup14] of Sylvester-Gallai type theorems for non-linear polynomials proposed to solve the case, and prove one of the easier conjectures for quadratic polynomials from [Shp18].&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devansh Shringi</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Deterministic and Randomized Algorithms for Factoring Univariate Polynomials Mod Prime-Powers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Ashish-Dwivedi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Deterministic and Randomized Algorithms for Factoring Univariate Polynomials Mod Prime-Powers" /><published>2019-11-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Ashish-Dwivedi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/Ashish-Dwivedi.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a series of 2 or 3 tutorial talks about factoring and root finding of a univariate polynomial f(x) mod a prime power p^k. The case of factoring f(x) mod p (special case k=1) is a very fundamental problem in computational number theory and theoretical computer science and finds applications in (but not limited to) cryptography, coding theory and other areas of mathematics. This problem has known efficient randomized algorithms but finding an efficient deterministic algorithm has been an enigma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, the general version of the problem, factoring f(x) mod p^k, has no known efficient randomized algorithm yet. The main objective of this talk series is to talk about the recent discoveries which takes us closer to this goal and also make aware the audience about the hurdles in the way. Mainly, an intuitive understanding of the problem will be given along with efficient randomized algorithm (Berthomieu, Lecerf and Quintin [BLQ13]) for finding roots, recent derandomization of [BLQ13] (D., Mittal and Saxena CCC’19) and factoring f(x) mod p^k for k&amp;lt;5 (D., Mittal and Saxena ISSAC’19).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 1&lt;/strong&gt; Talk was continued on 13th Nov 2019 at 3PM in KD102.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 2&lt;/strong&gt; Final part of the talk will be delivered by speaker on 15th Nov 2019 at 5PM in KD103&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashish Dwivedi</name></author><summary type="html">Abstract</summary></entry></feed>